Collection of Ephemera Relating to the Marketing of Books, 1742-2014: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Department of Rare Books and Special Collections.
- Publishing Ephemera Dated In the 1900s, 1900-1999; 11 boxes (10 partial)
  - Fogazzaro, Antonio: Eden Anto...translated by Theodore Wesley Koch, 1930; 37214; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus for this work published in conjunction with The Roxburghe Club of San Francisco; edition to be limited to 250 copies with illustrations by Rene Gockinga (one of which is reproduced here) and facsimiles from the Grenville and Charlemont copies of the Furioso, as well as a reproduction of a letter of Ariosto referring to this edition. Order form laid in.
  - Lewis, Oscar: Hearn and his biographers. The record of a literary controversy. Including the unpublished correspondence of Elizabeth Bisland, H.E. Krehbiel, Joseph Tunison, Henry Watkin and Dr. George M. Gould relating to the attacks on Hearn published after his death, and comprising the record of the bitterest controversy in American literary history. Together with a group of letters from Lafcadio Hearn to J. Tunison, 1930; 37223; portion of 1 box
    Hartford: Grabhorn Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; distributor's stamp on back.
  - Maclehose, James: The Glasgow University Press 1638-1931 with some notes on Scottish printing in the last three hundred years...with illustrations in photogravure and collotype, 37145; portion of 1 box
    Author: Maclehose, James
    Glasgow: Glasgow University Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus provides reviews, two specimen pages, and integral order form addressed to Messrs. Jackson, Wylie & Co. Text in red and black, previous fold.
  - Wood, Samuel: The cries of New-York, 1931; 37320; portion of 1 box
    Author: Wood, Samuel
    Bifolium, 12mo; Cries of New York, originally published by Samuel Wood in 1808; illustrated specimen page (25) provided.
  - Terry, Ellen: Ellen Terry and Bernard Shaw: A correspondence. Edited by Christopher St. John, 1931; 37074; portion of 1 box
    Author: Terry, Ellen
    New York: The Fountain Press
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for the first edition, limited to 1500 copies, of the Shaw-Terry letters, designed and printed by D.B. Updike of the Merrymount Press; specimen title page and two others (xxxvi, 167) included. Text in red and black, previous fold.
  - Gibbings, Robert: Season 1932. Mr. Robert Gibbings presents his world famous Golden Cockerel in its eleventh year in six completely new and original numbers., 36423; portion of 1 box
    Author: Gibbings, Robert
    Bershire, England: Golden Cockerel Press
    4to, unpaginated; illustrated t.p., prospectus for the season's upcoming titles from the press, which includes Hugh Walpole's "The Apple Trees with engravings by Lynton Lamb"; Lord Dunsany's "Lord Adrian, a play in three acts with engravings by Robert Gibbings"; Rhys Davies' "Daisy Matthews and other tales with four engravings by Agnes Miller Parker"; "Rummy, that noble game expounded in prose, poetry, diagram and engraving by A.E. Coppard & Robert Gibbings"; "Consequences: A complete story in the manner of the old parlous game of consequences in nine long chapters each by a different author"; "Sermons by Artists". Also includes a retrospectus of previous publication, amply illustrated with wood engravings. Also provides three book plates available from the press. Small stain to front cover and fold to back bottom left-hand corner. Lightly soiled.
  - Marlowe, Christopher: The complete works of Christopher Marlowe, 1932; 37154; portion of 1 box
    Author: Marlowe, Christopher
    London: Golden Hours Press
    4to, unpaginated; prospectus for this nine-volume set, with specimen page (50) and specimen plate (wood engravings by various artists). Previous book dealer's stamp to front cover.
  - Prospectus and catalogue of books published by the Halcyon Press...1932, 37313; portion of 1 box
    8vo, pp. 15; catalogue of books available from the Press, including works by Edgar Allen Poe, John Keats, John Milton, and Rainer Maria Rilke. Marginal notes.
  - How, Louis: The other Don Juan...Illustrations by Steele Savage, 1932; 37323; portion of 1 box
    Broadside, 4to (274 mm.); prospectus provides title page and specimen page (50) on verso.
  - Harrison of Paris presents for the autumn of 1932 two exceptional publications, 37287; portion of 1 box
    Paris: Harrison of Paris
    Single folded sheet, large 8vo; prospectus for two titles, Glenway Wescott's "A Calendar of Saints for Unbelievers" and "A Typographical Commonplace-book: Quotations and anecdotes variously printed"; a list of other titles available from the press printed on the back. Order form and specimen bifolium from the Calendar both laid in.
  - Polo, Marco: The travels of Marco Polo, 1933; 37341; portion of 1 box
    Author: Polo, Marco
    Rochester, New York: Printing House of Leo Hart
    3 ll., TLs from the publisher on the Press's letterhead addressed to Emerson G. Wulling; announcing the publication of this piece illustrated by Dwiggins.
  - Johnson, A.F.: Type designs: Their history and development, 1934; 37144; portion of 1 box
    Author: Johnson, A.F.
    London: Grafton & Co.
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for "an accout of the development of typography from the point of view of design carried down to the nineteenth century". Facsimile and integral order form included.
  - Nielsen, Lauritz: Dansk typografisk atlas 1482-1600, 1934; 37148; portion of 1 box
    Author: Nielsen, Lauritz
    København: Gyldendalske Boghandel
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus in Danish, German, English, and French; three facsimiles reprinted here.
  - Boltoin, Reginald Pelham: Indian life of long ago in the city of New York...with illustrations by the author, 1934; 37155; portion of 1 box
    Author: Boltoin, Reginald Pelham
    New York: Joseph Graham
    Single folded sheet, 4to; illustrated prospectus with a maps and specimen pages provided.
  - Irving, Washington: Abottsford and Newstead Abbey, 1935; 37109; portion of 1 box
    Author: Irving, Washington
    Detroit: Fine Book Circle
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus for "this souvenir of an American's literary pilgrimage to the homes of Scott and Byron" with specimen pages (74-75),
  - Parsons, George F.: The life and adventures of James W. Marshall, discoverer of gold in California...introduction & notes by G. Ezra Dane, 1935; 37225; portion of 1 box
    Author: Parsons, George F.
    Bifolium, large 8vo; illustrated prospectus, providing a facsimile of the title page. Text in black and tan, previous fold.
  - Hawthorne, Nathaniel: Tales, 1936; 37107; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus of a collection of "Hawthorne's best tales," illustrated with original wood-engravings by Paul McPharlin, the book's designer; includes specimen pages and illustration (117-119).
  - McPharlin, Paul: The fine book letter. December 1937, 37114; portion of 1 box
    Author: McPharlin, Paul
    8vo, pp. [17]-22, [1]; newsletter includes article "Open sesame: Some craftsmanly children's books" by Samuel Garfinkle with a list of fine children's books; reprint of an illustration from "In Old Kentucky," titled "Miss Katherine Hepburn as Madge".
  - McPharlin, Paul: The fine book letter. January-February 1937, 37115; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; newsletter includes "Of making many books" as well as a list of "Informative books on phases of new and old book making at less than $4 a volume".
  - McPharlin, Paul: The fine book letter. July-November 1937, 37112; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; newsletter includes "Summary of what has gone before" and a list of books on theater.
  - The fine book letter.March-June 1937, portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; newsletter includes "The dilemna of fine book distribution" and a list of books on theater.
  - Wagner, Henry R.: The plains and the Rockies, 1937; 37222; portion of 1 box
    Author: Wagner, Henry R.
    Bifolium, large 8vo; prospectus for a new and enlarged edition, edited by Charles L. Camp; limited to 500 copies. With the distributor's ticket pasted to front. Text in black and tan, previous fold.
  - St. Denis: Joan, the maid of Orleans. Being that portion of the Chronicles of St. Denis which deals with her life and times. From the Chroniques de France, printed in Paris, 1493. Translated by Pauline S. Sowers. With reproductions of some twenty woodcuts from the original edition and a bibliographical note on the work of Antoine Verard, 1938; 37218; portion of 1 box
    Author: St. Denis
    Single folded sheet, 8vo; prospectus for a work printed for Roy Vernon Sowers in an edition limited to 525 copies; illustrated specimen page provided. Text in red and black, previous fold.
  - Magna Carta and other charters of English liberties, in revised text and translation by Noël Denholm-Young, 1938; 37153; portion of 1 box
    London: Guyon House Press
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus for the press's first publication, "set in 16 point Bembo and in Albertus, with charter headings and tailpieces designed by Berthold Wolpe". Edition limited to 256 copies. Order form loosely inserted. Text in red and black.
  - Leale, John: Recollections of a Tule sailor by John Leale (1850-1932), master mariner, San Francisco Bay with interpolations by Marion Leale, 1939; 37080; portion of 1 box
    Author: Leale, John
    San Francisco: George Fields
    Bifolium, 8vo; prospectus of Leale's memoirs with annotations by his daughter Marion.
  - Meyers, William H.: Naval sketches of the war in California. Reproductions in full color of the sketches made by gunner William H. Meyers aboard the United States sloop "Dale" in 1846 and 1847 with a descriptive text by Captain Dudley W. Knox of the United States Navy and an introduction by President Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1939; 37217; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet, folded into six-sided brochure, 8vo; prospectus of a work published for Random House in an edition limited to 1000 copies. Integral order form addressed to Paul A. Struck, New York City.
  - Meyers, William H.: Naval sketches of the war in California. Reproductions in full color of the sketches made by gunner William H. Meyers aboard the United States sloop "Dale" in 1846 and 1847 with a descriptive text by Captain Dudley W. Knox of the United States Navy and an introduction by President Franklin D. Roosevelt, 1939; 37215; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet, folded into six-sided brochure, 8vo; prospectus of a work published for Random House in an edition limited to 1000 copies. Integral order form addressed to Random House. With Roosevelt's introduction, reprinted in Life magazine, 8/28/39, laid in.
  - Dante Alighieri: Third and final volume of the Comedy ["Heaven"]...American translation by Louis How, 1940; 37322; portion of 1 box
    Single sheet folded into 6-sided pamphlet, 8vo; press "Comments" and specimen page provided; order form laid in.
  - McPharlin, Paul: The fine book letter, January 1938-March 1941, 37110; portion of 1 box
    8vo, unpaginated; newsletter includes specimen pages from various titles available from the press and a check list of books in print.
  - Lincoln, Abraham: Lincoln's Kalamazoo address against extending slavery. Also his life by Joseph J. Lewis. Both annotated by Thomas I. Starr, 1941; 37106; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustrated prospectus includes two specimen pages and integral order form.
  - How, Louis: An evening with Ninon. A didactic poem containing a translation of Racine's Berenice...Decorations by Boris Artzybasheff, 1941; 37317; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; "printed in Caledonia type on Archer paper, with title page and frontispiece in two colors, (shown on inside pages of this announcement). Bound in blue cloth over boards, gold stamped, in slip case". Previous fold.
  - Graphis no. 9/10 1945, 37147; portion of 1 box
    Zurich, Switzerland: Amstutz & Herdeg Graphis Press
    16mo, various pagings; illustrations throughout; "In this miniature Graphis no complete articles but only sections of such are reproduced".
  - The new colophon. A book collectors' quarterly, 1948; 42464; portion of 1 box
    New York: Norbert Halliwell.
    Bifolium, 4to, text in black and orange; prospectus for the resuscitation of the Colophon "By the same staff--in the same spirit," giving the names of the editors and contributing editors, including W.A. Dwiggins and Alfred A. Knopf. Back leaf provides information on the format, advertising, and subscription prices.
    Filed under H.
  - Singer, Charles: The earliest chemical industry. An essay in the historical relations of economics & technology illustrated from the Alum trade...With a preface by Derek Spence, 1948; 39444; portion of 1 box
    Author: Singer, Charles
    London: Folio Society.
    Bifolium, folio; specimen plate; previous fold, mostly fine. Order form laid in.
  - Shipton, Clifford K.: Isaiah Thomas, printer, patriot, and philanthropist, 1948; 37337; portion of 1 box
    Author: Shipton, Clifford K.
    New York: Printing House of Leo Hart
    Broadside, oblong 16mo (83 x 139 mm.); postcard prospectus announcing the publication of the second title in the Printers' Valhalla Series. Addressed to Emerson G. Wulling and postmarked Jul. 8, 1948.
  - Programme 1949, 39440; portion of 1 box
    New York: Folio Society.
    12mo, pp. 10; printed self-wrappers; fine. New titles from the Society include Isaak Walton and Charles Cotton's "The Compleat Angler"; and "Grimm's Household Tales," illustrated by George Cruikshank. Color plate and order form addressed to distributor Philip C. Duschnes laid in. Subscriber feedback printed on back wrapper.
  - Swan, Bradford F.: Gregory Dexter of London and New England, 1949; 37338; portion of 1 box
    Author: Swan, Bradford F.
    Bifolium, large 8vo; illustrated prospectus for third title in the Printers' Valhalla Series; order form and typescript letter on Press's letterhead laid in.
  - Autumn list 1950, 37201; portion of 1 box
    London: Golden Cockerel Press
    8vo, unpaginated; illustrated catalogue of new titles from the press. Philip C. Duschnes, distributor.
  - Komensky, John Amos: The labyrinth of the world and the paradise of the heart...translated by Count Lutzow. Illustrations by Dorothea Braby, 1950; 37205; portion of 1 box
    Author: Komensky, John Amos
    Bifolium, 8vo; illustrated prospectus for this edition limited to 370 copies; specimen page (30) and illustration included. US distributor Philip C. Duschnes, New York. Order form and pre-addressed envelope to the distributor loosely inserted. Text in black and tan, previous fold.
  - 1951 prospectus, portion of 1 box
    12mo, pp. 15; illustrations; original brown pictorial wrappers, fine. Titles for the year's series include Anthony Trollope's "Mary Gresley and other stories" and "The Complete Poems of Emily Brontë. Special announcement, order form, and envelope from the American distributor Philip C. Duschnes laid in. Advertisements for the folio society and Bruce Rogers' Twelve Moneths and Christmas Day laid in.
  - 1951 prospectus, 39441; portion of 1 box
    12mo, pp. 15; illustrations; original brown pictorial wrappers, fine. Titles for the year's series include Anthony Trollope's "Mary Gresley and other stories" and "The Complete Poems of Emily Brontë. Special announcement, order form, and envelope from the American distributor Philip C. Duschnes laid in. With original envelope in which the catalogue was mailed.
  - Caesar, Julius: Julius Caesar's commentaries. A mondern rendering by Somerset de Chair. Engravings by Clifford Webb, 1951; 37207; portion of 1 box
    Author: Caesar, Julius
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus for this edition limited to 320 copies; specimen page (135) and illustration included. Typed letter, signed, on Story Classics letterhead from J.I. Rodale and order form with pre-addressed envelope all loosely inserted.
  - Beaumont, Francis: Salmacis and Hermaphroditus. A poem attributed to Francis Beaumont. Edited by Gwyn Jones with ten engravings in colour by John Buckland-Wright, 1951; 37203; portion of 1 box
    Author: Beaumont, Francis
    Bifolium, folio; color illustrated prospectus for this edition limited to 380 copies; specimen page (34) and illustration provided. American distributor Story Classics, Emmaus, Pennsylvania. Previous fold.
  - M'Ilvaine, William, Jr.: Sketches of scenery and notes of personal adventure in California & Mexico...with a foreword by Robert G. Cleland & reproductions of the sixteen lithographic plates, 1951; 39360; portion of 1 box
    Author: M'Ilvaine, William, Jr.
    San Francisco: Grabhorn Press.
    Bifolium, folio; printed in red and black; previous fold, mostly fine. Prospectus for a title printed for the Book Club of California in an edition of 400 copies.
  - Prospectus 1952, 39443; portion of 1 box
    Oblong 16mo, unpaginated; illustrations; original blue pictorial wrappers, fine. Titles for the year's series include William Shakespeare's "Antony and Cleopatra," introduction by Sir Laurence Olivier; and "The Last Days of Shelley and Byron". Order form and envelope addressed to the American distributor Philip C. Duschnes laid in. With original envelope in which the catalogue was mailed.
  - 1952 catalog, 37202; portion of 1 box
    8vo, unpaginated; illustrated catalogue of new titles from the press; typed letter, signed, from the distributor on "Story Classics" letterhead and order form with preaddressed envelope to Story Classics, Emmaus, Pennsylvania, loosely inserted.
  - Hartnoll, Phyllis: The Grecian enchanted...with eight aquatints by John Buckland-Wright, 1952; 37204; portion of 1 box
    Author: Hartnoll, Phyllis
    Bifolium, folio; illustrated prospectus for this limited edition of 360 copies. US distributor Story Classics, Emmaus, Pennsylvania. Previous fold.
  - Rabelais, Francois: Catalogue of the choice books found by Pantagruel in the Abbey of St. Victor...Translator: Walter Klinefelter, a student of catalogues, 1952; 37228; portion of 1 box
    Author: Rabelais, Francois
    Burlingame, California: Grabhorn Press
    Bifolium, 4to; prospectus for a book printed for William P. Wreden, introduced here by Nathan van Patten. Edition limited to 200 copies. Previous fold.
  - Prospectus 1953, 39442; portion of 1 box
    12mo, pp. 19; illustrations; original pink pictorial wrappers, a bit soiled. Titles for the year's series include Henry Fielding's "The History of Joseph Andrews," Honoré de Balzac's "Eugénie Grandet"; and Emlyn Williams's "Readings from Dickens". List of previous publications bound in back. Order form and envelope from the American distributor Philip C. Duschnes laid in.
  - Autumn 1954. British hand-made books, 37182; portion of 1 box
    Emmaus, PA: Golden Cockerel Private Press
    12mo, pp. 39; illustrated catalogue for new titles from the press; order forms and letter from the distributor, Rodale Books, loosely inserted.
  - 1955-1956, 37200; portion of 1 box
    Reading, Berkshire: Golden Cockerel Private Press
    12mo, pp. 47; illustrated catalogue of recent titles from the press, including Percy Bysshe Shelley's "Zastrozzi" with illustrations by Cecil Keeling; and "Cockalorum: A Bibliography of the Press". Order form addressed to the distributor, G.F. Sims, loosely inserted.
  - Spring 1955, 37199; portion of 1 box
    New York: Golden Cockerell Private Press
    12mo, pp. 24; illustrated catalogue of recent publications from the press, including a new edition of the Green Knight. Order form and pre-addressed envelope to the American distributor, Philip C. Duschnes, loosely inserted.
  - Prospectus for Pleasure, 1961; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, printed in green and black on greenish-yellow paper. Invitation for a 2-day event hosted by the Grolier Club and Zamorano Club.
  - [Collection of prospectuses], 1963; 39095; portion of 1 box
    Newnham, Tasmania: Wattle Grove Press
    7 leaves of various sizes stapled together; previous folds, else fine. Addressed to American book collectors; mission statement laid in.
  - Skelton, R.A.: James Cook, surveyor of Newfoundland. Being a collection of charts of the coasts of Newfoundland and Labradore, &c. drawn from original surveys taken by James Cook and Michael Lane. London, Thomas Jefferys, 1769-1770. Reproduced in facsimile from the copy in the library of the University of California at Los Angeles, 1965; 37227; portion of 1 box
    Author: Skelton, R.A.
    Bifolium, folio; prospectus for this facsimile edition printed for David Magee and limited to 365 copies. Previous fold.
  - Baird, Joseph Armstrong, Jr.: California's pictorial letter sheet, 1849-1869, 1967; 37244; portion of 1 box
    Author: Baird, Joseph Armstrong, Jr.
    San Francisco: Grabhorn-Hoyem
    Bifolium, folio; edition printed for David Magee and limited to 475 copies. Order form laid in.Text in red and black, previous folds. With envelope in which this prospectus was originally mailed, addressed to Emerson G. Wulling.
  - Prospectus & retrospectus 1970 [cover title], 39832; portion of 1 box
    Boston: David R. Godine.
    8vo, unpaginated; illustrations; original blue printed wrappers, fine. Titles include Thoreau's "Civil Disobedience"; and James Agee's "The Last Letter to Father Flye"; a list of books in progress provided in the back. Price list laid in.
  - Prospectus of books, 1970; 39826; portion of 1 box
    Brookline, Massachusetts: David R. Godine.
    8vo, unpaginated; text printed in red and black; original brown printed wrappers, printed in black and brown; fine. Titles from the catalogue include Henry David Thoreau's "A Plea for Captain John Brown"; James Agee's "The Last Letter to Father Flye"; and Walt Whitman's "Specimen Days". Discount schedule and policy laid in.
  - Prospectus of books, 1970; portion of 1 box
    8vo, unpaginated; text printed in red and black; original olive pictorial wrappers, printed in black and brown; fine. Titles from the catalogue include Henry David Thoreau's "A Plea for Captain John Brown"; James Agee's "The Last Letter to Father Flye"; and Walt Whitman's "Specimen Days". Specimen pages from the works of John Wesley Powell laid in.
  - Freeman, Arthur: Assays of bias. Poems, 1970; 39840; portion of 1 box
    Bifolium, 8vo; printed in grey and black; fine. Provides 2 specimen poems. Order form laid in.
  - Powell, John Wesley: The selected prose, 1970; 39839; portion of 1 box
    Author: Powell, John Wesley
    Broadside, 8vo (212 mm.); printed on tan paper in green and black; fine. Integral order form.
  - Prospectus of books, 1970; 39358; portion of 1 box
    8vo, unpaginated; text printed in red and black; original olive pictorial wrappers, printed in black and brown; fine. Titles from the catalogue include Henry David Thoreau's "A Plea for Captain John Brown"; James Agee's "The Last Letter to Father Flye"; and Walt Whitman's "Specimen Days". Envelope laid in.
  - The Bible designed to be read as literature, 1970; 37084; portion of 1 box
    London: Folio Society
    Bifolium, 4to; illustrated prospectus for this edition of the Bible, an edition illustrated with 32 Old Master drawings, including works by Dürer, Raphael, Rubens, Rembrandt, and Blake. Integral order form on back page for either the standard edition or the leather bound edition. Previous fold.
  - Dickens, Charles: David Copperfield, 1970; 37140; portion of 1 box
    London: Fraser Press
    Portfolio, 8vo; prospectus announcing the limited edition of Dicken's novel, illustrations by "Phiz" lithographed by the Curwen Press, bound by the Wigmore Bindery. Also includes prospectuses for other titles, each printed on separate Broadsides; type letter, signed from Gordon Fraser to Emerson G. Wulling and order form both loosely inserted along with the press's mission statement.